Guide to the Frances Hesselbein Papers, 1942-2013 AIS.2013.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Frances Hesselbein Personal Papers, ca. 1930s-1940s, 1955-2014; B.
  - Events, 1986-2012; V.
    - West Chester University Commencement, May 14, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 26)
    - The Philanthropy Workshop, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 27)
    - Thomas Kolditz retirement ceremony, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 28)
    - Boston University Executive Development Roundtable, 2011-2012 (Box 24, Folder 29)
    - National Human Services Assembly meeting, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 30)
    - National Principals Leadership Institute conference, 2011-2012 (Box 24, Folder 31)
    - Hesselbein Global Academy, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 32)
    - Marshall Goldsmith dinner, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 33)
    - Chief Executive of the Year, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 34)
    - NYC Leadership Center Movement Day, 2012 (Box 24, Folder 35)
    - Babson College presentation, March 2012 (Box 24, Folder 36)
    - Easton Children's Home 125th anniversary, undated (Box 24, Folder 37)
    - The Clay Haus reception, undated (Box 24, Folder 38)
    - Conversation with John Gardner notes, undated (Box 24, Folder 39)
    - Creating Positive Organizational Change, undated (Box 24, Folder 40)
  - Nonprofit Organizations, 1985-2013; VI.
    This series contains the information Frances Hesselbein collected on various nonprofit organizations, including those of which she was an advisor/board member. There are annual reports of the organizations included here, as well as publications specific to the nonprofits, and information of other advisors/board members/personnel. The materials are arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the organization. Materials for this series date from 1985 to 2013.
    - ACE Mentor Program, 2008 (Box 24, Folder 41)
    - American India Foundation, 2005-2006 (Box 24, Folder 42)
    - Asian Institute of Management, 2000s (Box 24, Folder 43)
    - Bennett College, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 44)
    - Big Brothers Big Sisters, September 2000 (Box 24, Folder 45)
    - The Board Cafe, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 46)
    - Bright China Management Institute, 2008-2013 (Box 24, Folder 47)
    - The Broad Superintendents Academy, 2000s (Box 24, Folder 48)
    - The Center for Collaborative Education, May 2002 (Box 24, Folder 49)
    - Council on Accreditation, September 2006 (Box 24, Folder 50)
    - Council of Michigan Foundations, 2001 (Box 24, Folder 51)
    - Defense Orientation Conference Association, Inc., June 2012 (Box 24, Folder 52)
    - Eisenhower Exchange Fellowships, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 53)
    - Eurasia Foundation, October 1993 (Box 24, Folder 54)
    - Foundation for African Non Governmental Organisations Management materials, 2000-2012 (Box 24, Folder 55)
    - FANGOM Zambia information, March 2001 (Box 24, Folder 56)
    - FANGOM documents, 2000s (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Fundacion Compromiso, 2000s (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Generals in Transition, 2003-2008 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - George Bush School of Government and Public Service, 2006 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Global Women - Partners in Philanthropy, Spring 2012 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - GreatHearts School, 2010 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Harlem Educational Activities Fund, Inc., December 1996 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Independent Sector, 2000s (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Institute for International Education, 2009-2010 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - KidsPeace, 1990s (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - The Leadership Institute, 1990s (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - The Leadership Network, 1988-1990, 2007 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Lovincer Children Foundation, October 2011 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Mary Baker Eddy Library, 2003 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Melbourne Citymission, 2004-2005 (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Military Child Education Coalition, 2003-2012 (Box 25, Folder 15-16)
    - Ministry of Gender Equality - Republic of Korea, 2000s (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Mutual of America Foundation Board materials, 1995-1997 (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Mutual of America Foundation correspondence and publications, 1992-1995, 2010-2013 (Box 25, Folder 19)
    - Mutual of America publications, 1996-2004 (Box 25, Folder 20)
    - Mutual of America Program/Marketing Committee meeting, 8/26/10 (Box 25, Folder 21)
    - Mutual of America presentations, 1992, 2012 (Box 25, Folder 22)
    - Mutual of America investment information, 2000s (Box 25, Folder 23)
    - Mutual of America 40th Anniversary, 9/20/85 (Box 25, Folder 24)
    - Mutual of America Community Partnership Award Selection Committee materials, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 25)
    - National Crime Prevention Council, 2005-2009 (Box 25, Folder 26)
    - National Urban League Affiliate Resource Manual, 1/22/04 (Box 25, Folder 27-29)
    - Nonprofit Almanac, 1996-1997 (Box 25, Folder 30)
    - NPR, June 2001 (Box 25, Folder 31)
    - Partnership for American Veterans Employment and Education Solutions, undated (Box 25, Folder 32)
    - Volunteers of America, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 33)
    - Volunteers of America Communications Guide, 2001-2006 (Box 25, Folder 34)
    - Warrior to Citizen, 2010-2011 (Box 25, Folder 35)
    - The Washington Center, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 36)
    - World Vision, 2002 (Box 25, Folder 37)
    - Yuhan-Kimberly, 2008-2009 (Box 25, Folder 38)
  - Speeches, 1976-2013; VII.
    This series contains speeches made by Frances Hesselbein, speeches made about her, and her collection of speech reference files. The speeches are generally transcripts of presentations, though there are some reading copies. They are arranged chronologically, with the undated materials present at the end of each subseries. Speeches that were originally grouped with extraneous materials, such as an invitation to the event at which the speech was given, were separated out of the rest and given individual files. These speeches appear after the rest of the chronologically ordered materials. The speech reference files were kept in their original order and retain the names given to them by Hesselbein and her associates.
    - Hesselbein speeches, 1976-1987; 1.
      - Speeches, 1976-1987
        - "What It Means to Belong", 1976; 1. (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Salem Methodist Church, March 15, 1981; 2.
        - Deloitte Haskins and Sells - "The Female Executive--Reconciling Career and Personal Goals", October 15, 1981; 3.
        - Martin Luther King, Jr. Birthday celebration, January 14, 1983; 4.
        - United Way, January 22, 1985; 5.
        - 50th Anniversary American Association of Fund-Raising Counsel, May 1, 1985; 6.
        - United Way - "Managing for the Mission", June 3, 1985; 7.
        - National Meetings of Executive Directors final plenary, January 1986; 8.
        - March of Dimes - "Building a Winning Team for Diversity", March 25, 1986; 9.
        - American Management Association, May 1, 1986; 10.
        - Meeting of Executive Directors, January 1987; 11a.
        - "Opening Remarks" - Executive Directors Meeting, January, 1987; 11b.
        - Closing speech - National meeting of Executive Directors, January 1987; 12.
        - Speech to Hemlock Girl Scout Council, January 29, 1987; 13.
        - Academy of Senior Professionals - "Management Leadership in the Third Sector", February 5, 1987; 14.
        - Greater Minneapolis Girl Scout Council, March 6, 1987; 15.
        - National Girl Scouts Staff video message, March 12, 1987; 16.
        - Speech to Talus Rock Girl Scout Council, April 9, 1987; 17.
        - Meeting of Executive Directors - Opening Remarks, April 13, 1987; 18.
        - United Way of America 100th Anniversary - "A Tribute to America's Volunteers", April 26, 1987; 19.
        - Lake Erie College Commencement, May 10, 1987; 20.
        - Buena Vista College Commencement, May 17, 1987; 21.
        - Mutual of America Distinguished Community Service Award dinner for Sister Mary Maurita Sengelaub, June 6, 1987; 22.
        - Address to Women Executives, June 7, 1987; 23.
        - Top 17 Meeting - "Comments on Volunteer/Staff Partnerships", July 7, 1987; 24.
        - Addendum to the Girl Scouts National Program Conference, 1987; 25.
        - "Major Issues and Challenges - Now to Year 2000", September 1987; 26.
        - Mrs. Hesselbein's message to Girl Scout Councils, September 1987; 27.
        - Tribute to Peter Drucker, October 21, 1987; 28.
        - Opening Remarks - AGSES National Convention, October 26, 1987; 29.
        - National Executive Director's Address - 44th Council Session, October 26, 1987; 30.
        - "Farewell speech for Marge Phelan", November 13, 1987; 31.
        - Indiana Meeting of Executive Staff - "Preparing for the Future: Developing a Contemporary Image", November 13, 1987; 32.
        - Seminar for Council Teams Piloting New Field Structures - Opening Address, November 20, 1987; 33.
        - Chicago Field Center - Script for 1988 Pluralism Conferences, December 8, 1987; 34.
      - Speeches, 1988
        - Executive Directors Meeting - Keynote speech, February 1988; 1. (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - "Managing Volunteers" - National Volunteer Leaders' Assembly, March 19, 1988; 2.
        - Presentation to Critical Issues in Philanthropy Group, May 9, 1988; 3
        - Speech to Swift Water Girl Scout Council, May 11, 1988; 4.
        - Remarks at Luncheon Honoring Thomas W. Kelly, May 17, 1988; 5.
        - Speech to Penn's Woods Girl Scout Council - 25th Anniversary Celebration, May 19, 1988; 6.
        - "Words Change, Values Don't", June 1988; 7.
        - Speech to Rio Grande Girl Scout Council, October 8, 1988; 8.
        - Partnership Project Symposium - Opening welcome speech, October 21, 1988; 9.
        - "Honoring Diversity" - Organizational Development Network conference, November 2, 1988; 10.
        - Speech to Volunteers of America, November 7, 1988; 11.
        - GSUSA National Meeting of Presidents and Executive Directors - Opening meeting, November 11, 1988; 12.
        - GSUSA National Meeting of Presidents and Executive Directors - Closing meeting, November 13, 1988; 13.
        - GSUSA President's message, 1988; 14.
      - Speeches, 1989
        - "Thinking Day" audiotape speech, February 10, 1989; 1. (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - Notes on Innovation in Girl Scouting meeting with Kellogg Foundation, March 6, 1989; 2.
        - Closing remarks - teleconference from Washington, D.C., March 31, 1989; 3.
        - Remarks at meeting on 500 Years of American Clothing, April 18, 1989; 4.
        - Transcript of audio tape sent to Libbie Vernon, April 21, 1989; 5.
        - Draft of opening speech - Staff training for Girl Guides of Canada, May 2, 1989; 6.
        - "Take the Lead" - Meeting of San Diego-Imperial Council, May 18, 1989; 7.
        - Welcome speech at Retirees' Luncheon, May 25, 1989; 8.
        - Speech to new presidents, June 17, 1989; 9.
        - Introduction to Corporate Management Team Retreat, June 1989; 10.
        - Speech at 1989 National Program Conference Luncheons, July 1989; 11.
        - Speech at Evaluation Conference - GSUSA Pilot Project on Field Structure, August 29, 1989; 12.
        - Address to Greater St. Louis Council luncheon, September 14, 1989; 13.
        - First Draft for Opening - National Meeting of Executive, September 15, 1989; 14a.
        - Opening speech - National Meeting of Executive Directors, September 15, 1989; 14b.
        - Closing remarks - National Meeting of Executive Directors, September 17, 1989; 15.
        - Speech for Lake Erie Girl Scout Council, October 31, 1989; 16.
        - Mandel Center Distinguished Public Lecture (Draft), November 1, 1989; 17a.
        - "The New Nonprofit: Combining Efficiency and Purpose" - Mandel Center Distinguished Public Lecture, November 1, 1989; 17b.
        - National Center for Innovation - Innovation conference, November 2, 1989; 18.
        - Donor's Platform Speech - Council of Michigan Foundations, November 10, 1989; 19.
        - "The Third Sector: Its Importance and Its Needs" - A Day with Peter Drucker event, November 18, 1989; 20.
      - Speeches, 1990
        - Speech to Stanford University Graduate School of Business - Public Management Program, February 2, 1990; 1. (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - Speech to Christian Management Association, February 1990; 2.
        - "Attributes of Leadership" - Northrop Corporation, April 4, 1990; 3.
        - Bell South, April 23, 1990; 4.
        - Speech materials excerpt list, undated; 5.
        - Speech materials subject files list, undated; 6.
        - Speech schedule, 1990-1993; 7.
        - Ohio State Biennial - W. Arthur Cullman Symposium, May 3, 1990; 8.
        - GMI Institute Commencement address, June 22, 1990; 9.
        - "CESSE '90" - Council of Engineering and Scientific Society Executives, July 11, 1990; 10.
        - The Salvation Army (Draft), September 21, 1990; 11a.
        - The Salvation Army (Revised), September 21, 1990; 11b.
        - University of Notre Dame - MBA Marketing Association, October 2, 1990; 12.
        - "Managing for Success in the 1990's" - National Executive Service Corps Leadership Conference, November 9, 1990; 13.
      - Speeches, 1991
        - "Managing for the Mission: New thinking for New Management" (Draft) - Best of America Conference and Exposition, January 30, 1991; 1a. (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - "Managing for the Mission: New thinking for New Management" - Best of America Conference and Exposition, January 30, 1991; 1b.
        - "Charting the Course of Consumer Service: Leadership Challenge of the 90's" - National Rural Electric Cooperative Association, February 5, 1991; 2.
        - The Communities Foundation of Texas, February 27, 1991; 3.
        - Association for Quality and Participation, February 27, 1991; 4.
        - "Nonprofit Management in the 1990s: An Adventure in Leadership" - National Society of Fund Raising Executives, March 4, 1991; 5.
        - "Nonprofit Management in the 1990s: An Adventure in Leadership" - United Way of Wyoming Valley, March 7, 1991; 6.
        - Independent Sector Research Forum, March 15, 1991; 7.
        - Adventure in Excellence seminar, April 6, 1991; 8.
        - United States Department of Agriculture, April 17, 1991; 9.
        - "Managing in the 90's -- The Changing Paradigm" (Draft) - Indiana University Center on Philanthropy, April 19, 1991; 10a.
        - "Managing in the 90's -- The Changing Paradigm" - Indiana University Center on Philanthropy, April 19, 1991; 10b.
        - "Experiences of a Paradigm Breaker" - The Conference Board, May 7, 1991; 11.
        - Wilson College Commencement speech, May 19, 1991; 12.
        - Speech to Atlanta Rotary Club, June 3, 1991; 13.
        - Speech to Allentown College, June 4, 1991; 14.
        - Executive Development Associates, June 7, 1991; 15.
        - "Managing Effective Organizations in the 1990s" - American Public Power Association, June 19, 1991; 16.
        - "Managing Your Mission: Lessons of Effective Leadership from the Nonprofit Organization" - BusinessWeek, June 20, 1991; 17.
        - Speech schedule, 1990-1991; 18.
        - "Volunteers: They Aren't Who and What They Used to Be" - Council for Advancement and Support of Education, July 16, 1991; 1. (Box 26, Folder 6)
        - Lutheran Leadership Conference (Drafts), July 18, 1991; 3a.
        - Lutheran Leadership Conference, July 18, 1991; 3b.
        - Northrop Corporation, July 20, 1991; 3.
        - "Managerial Innovation for the '90s: Breaking the Paradigms in Healthcare" - American Hospital Association Convention, July 30, 1991; 4.
        - Head Start, August 9, 1991; 5.
        - "Identifying and Mobilizing Volunteers: An Exchange with Frances Hesselbein" - American Society for Association Executives, August 11, 1991; 6.
        - "Managing for the Mission" - American Society for Association Executives, August 12, 1991; 7.
        - "Confronting Barriers to Leadership" - Kellogg Foundation, September 10, 1991; 8.
        - Pennsylvania Association of Colleges and Universities, September 22, 1991; 9.
        - "Positioning Yourself to Make a Difference" (Draft) - Leadership Network Conference, September 26, 1991; 10a.
        - "Positioning Yourself to Make a Difference" - Leadership Network Conference, September 26, 1991; 10b.
        - "Creating a World of Difference" - Financial Women International, September 30, 1991; 11.
        - The Board Member Institute, October 3, 1991; 12.
        - Executive Women in Human Services, Inc., October 29, 1991; 13.
        - "Volunteerism: Change, Challenge, and Contribution in the '90s" - The Samaritan Institute, November 2, 1991; 14.
        - "Managing in the Knowledge Society" - Fordham University First Boston Lecture, December 9, 1991; 15.
      - Speeches, 1992
        - Speech schedule, 1990-1993; 1. (Box 26, Folder 7)
        - "Managing for the Mission" - American Lung Association Conference of Executives, January 22, 1992; 2.
        - Teleconference - The Drucker Foundation, February 18, 1992; 3.
        - "Managing Change/Leadership in the 90's" - Visiting Nurse Association, March 5, 1992; 4.
        - Protestant Health and Human Services Assembly, March 10, 1992; 5.
        - "Changing Paradigms of Leadership" - University of San Francisco, March 18, 1992; 6.
        - Volunteer Center of Sonoma County, March 19, 1992; 7.
        - "Coming Home" - Talus Rock Girl Scout Council, April 20, 1992; 8.
        - "Change, Covenant and Commitment to Leadership" - Allentown College of Saint Francis de Sales, May 16, 1992; 9.
        - "I Dare You" - The General Assembly of YMCAs, July 7, 1992; 10.
        - Agency for International Development, July 10, 1992; 11.
        - "Focus on the Customer" (Drafts) - National Council of La Raza, July 20, 1992; 12a.
        - "Focus on the Customer" - National Council of La Raza, July 20, 1992; 12b.
        - The Trinity Forum handwritten speech as given, September 24, 1992; 13.
        - United Way of Sacramento Valley, October 4, 1992; 14.
        - "The Anatomy of Planned Giving" - National Committee on Planned Giving National Conference, October 10, 1992; 1. (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - American Health Information Management Association, October 13, 1992; 2.
        - CGSC speech, October 30, 1992; 3.
        - "Leadership in the '90s" drafts - University of Southern California, November 1, 1992; 4.
        - "Crossing the Voluntary/Statutory Barrier" - Office of Public Management, November 25, 1992; 5.
        - New York University, December 10, 1992; 6.
      - Speeches, 1993
        - "The Spirit of Women - 1993" - Allentown, January 8, 1993; 1. (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - "Managing for the Mission" - Wharton School, February 1, 1993; 2.
        - WomanCare - Allentown Hospital, March 19, 1993; 3.
        - "Visionary Leadership for the '90s" - Club 100 of the Music Center, April 15, 1993; 4.
        - "Blurring Boundaries and Emerging Challenges for Today's Leaders" - Claremont Graduate School Executive Management Program, May 1, 1993; 5.
        - University of Pittsburgh, May 5, 1993; 6.
        - Easton Chamber of Commerce, May 19, 1993; 7.
        - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Expo for Nonprofit Organizations, May 26, 1993; 8.
        - Atlanta Executive Service Corps, June 3, 1993; 9.
        - Anderson Consulting Presentation, June 4, 1993; 10.
        - "Managing for the Future" - Connecticut Valley Girl Scout Dinner, June 14, 1993; 11.
        - McFeely Award Acceptance speech, June 17, 1993; 12.
        - "Business or Charity? What Are We?" (Handwritten Draft) - Family Service America Large Agency Executive's Conference, June 24, 1993; 13a.
        - "Business or Charity? What Are We?" - Family Service America Large Agency Executive's Conference, June 24, 1993; 13b.
        - "Shaping and Managing Nonprofit Organizations in the '90s" - American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, July 8, 1993; 14.
        - American Association of Retired Persons, July 12, 1993; 15. (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - "Fulfilling Your Nonprofit Mission in the '90s" - National Executive Service Corps, July 26, 1993; 16.
        - "Innovation: A Leadership Imperative" - Peter Drucker Award for Canadian Nonprofit Innovation, November 3, 1993; 17.
        - "Managing for Results: Meeting the Challenge of Accountability" - Opening plenary, November 9, 1993; 18.
        - "The Enterprise Beyond" - National Center for Nonprofit Boards, November 1993; 19.
        - "Transforming Public Service" - Kellogg Center, November 1993; 20.
        - "Listening to the Customer: Lessons Learned" - The National Performance Review, December 13, 1993; 21.
      - Speeches, 1994
        - "The Challenge of Accountability", February 17, 1994; 1. (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - "Transformations" - Chief Executives Agenda Seminar, March 1, 1994; 2.
        - Project 1994 Annual Dinner speech, April 2, 1994; 3.
        - "Driving Strategic Leadership Through Mission, Vision and Goals" (Drafts) - International Strategic Management Conference, April 12, 1994; 4a.
        - "Driving Strategic Leadership Through Mission, Vision and Goals" - International Strategic Management Conference, April 12, 1994; 4b.
        - "Leaders for the Future" - University of Nebraska Commencement, May 6, 1994; 5.
        - "In the Company of Women" (Drafts) - Simmons College, May 13, 1994; 6a.
        - "In the Company of Women" - Simmons College, May 13, 1994; 6b.
        - "New York Cares", July 14, 1994; 7.
        - "Leadership for the Future" (Drafts) - International Association of Business Communicators, November 7, 1994; 8a.
        - "Leadership for the Future" - International Association of Business Communicators, November 7, 1994; 8b.
        - "How Does the CEO of a Nonprofit Organization Exert Leadership Without Dominating the Board?" - National Center for Boards of Directors, November 14, 1994; 1. (Box 26, Folder 12)
        - Lutheran Church Extension Fund - Fall Conference, November 18, 1994; 2.
        - "The Nonprofit Organization as a Modern Service Corporation New Trends and Developments Until the Year 2000" - University of Vienna, November 1994; 3.
      - Speeches, 1995
        - "The Nonprofit Sector - Critical Governance and Management Issues" - National Urban League annual meeting, January 12, 1995; 1. (Box 26, Folder 13)
        - Points of Light Family Matters Leadership Forum, January 1995; 2.
        - The Agency Executives Council of Long Island's United Way Conference (Drafts), February 3, 1995; 3a.
        - The Agency Executives Council of Long Island's United Way Conference, February 3, 1995; 3b.
        - "Managing for the Mission" - Ohio Department of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities, March 16, 1995; 4.
        - The University of North Carolina at Wilmington - LQC Lamar Society, April 1, 1995; 5.
        - "Building Connections: Tools for Tomorrow" - Framing the Future: New Tools for Social Sector Leaders Conference, April 1995; 6.
        - "They came to Topton" - Benefactors' Dinner for The Lutheran Home at Topton, April 20, 1995; 7.
        - Business Hall of Fame - Greater Johnstown/Cambria Country, April 21, 1995; 8.
        - "Managing Beyond the Millennium", May 2, 1995; 9.
        - GALA Dedication Opening the School of Business and School of Education Complex - California State University, May 11, 1995; 10.
        - "We Pay for What We Value" - General Electric Fund Conference, May 16, 1995; 11.
        - "The Power Within" - Hewlett Packard Technical/Professional Women's Conference, June 2, 1995; 12.
        - "Management and Leadership" - Women and Company, June 6, 1995; 13.
        - "A Society of Three Sectors", June 7, 1995; 14.
        - "Building Commitment and Leadership", June 8, 1995; 15.
        - CSC Index Conference speech, June 12, 1995; 16.
        - American Association of Retired People (AARP) conference, June 13, 1995; 17.